Roles

The HTML articles on this page are of type ies:State. Claims are facts about entities expressed in the present tense. Facts expressed in an article are assumed to be consistent. Facts across different articles are only assumed to be consistent if the states associated with each article are consistent. Here, that means the articles describe states at "about the same time".

Tacitus, Annals 1.3:

And yet Augustus had appointed Germanicus, Drusus's offspring, to the command of eight legions on the Rhine, ...

Germanicus is in command of eight legions in Germany.

Tacitus, Annals 1.7:

Sextus Pompeius and Sextus Apuleius, the consuls, were the first to swear allegiance to Tiberius Caesar, and in their presence the oath was taken by Seius Strabo and Caius Turranius, respectively the commander of the praetorian cohorts and the superintendent of the corn supplies.

Seius Strabo is in command of the Praetorian Guard.
Caius Turranius is superintendent of the corn supplies.

Tacitus, Annals 1.24:

With them too was the commander of the praetorians, Aelius Sejanus, who had been associated with his own father, Strabo, had great influence with Tiberius, and was to advise and direct the young prince, and to hold out punishment or reward to the soldiers.

Aelius Sejanus is in command of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 1.31:

There were two armies on the bank of the Rhine; that named the upper army had Caius Silius for general; the lower was under the charge of Aulus Caecina. The supreme direction rested with Germanicus, then busily employed in conducting the assessment of Gaul.

Caius Silius is in command of the upper army, stationed in Germany.
Aulus Caecina is in command of the lower army, stationed in Germany.
Germanicus is superior to Caius Silius and Aulus Caecina.

The troops under the control of Silius, with minds yet in suspense, watched the issue of mutiny elsewhere; but the soldiers of the lower army fell into a frenzy, which had its beginning in the men of the twenty first and fifth legions, and into which the first and twentieth were also drawn. For they were all quartered in the same summer-camp, in the territory of the Ubii, enjoying ease or having only light duties.

The twenty-first legion is part of the lower army.
The fifth legion is part of the lower army.
The first legion is part of the lower army.
The twentieth legion is part of the lower army.

Tacitus, Annals 1.37:

Germanicus went to the Upper Army, and the second, thirteenth, and sixteenth legions, without any delay, accepted from him the oath of allegiance. The fourteenth hesitated a little, but their money and the discharge were offered even without their demanding it.

The second legion is part of the upper army.
The thirteenth legion is part of the upper army.
The sixteenth legion is part of the upper army.
The fourteenth legion is part of the upper army.

Tacitus, Annals 1.16:

This was the state of affairs at Rome when a mutiny broke out in the legions of Pannonia, ... In the summer camp three legions were quartered, under the command of Junius Blaesus, ...

Junius Blaesus is in command of three legions in Pannonia.

Tacitus, Annals 1.23:

Two legions, the eighth and the fifteenth, were actually drawing swords against each other, the former demanding the death of a centurion, whom they nicknamed Sirpicus, while the men of the fifteenth defended him, but the soldiers of the ninth interposed their entreaties, and when these were disregarded, their menaces.

The eighth legion is stationed in Pannonia.
The fifteenth legion is stationed in Pannonia.
The ninth legion is stationed in Pannonia.

Tacitus, Annals 1.44:

Away they hurried hither and thither, altered men, and dragged the chief mutineers in chains to Caius Caetronius, commander of the first legion, who tried and punished them one by one in the following fashion.

Caius Caetronius is in commmand of the first legion.

Tacitus, Annals 2.2:

After the death of Phraates and the succeeding kings in the bloodshed of civil wars, there came to Rome envoys from the chief men of Parthia, in quest of Vonones, his eldest son. Caesar thought this a great honour to himself, and loaded Vonones with wealth. The barbarians, too, welcomed him with rejoicing, as is usual with new rulers.

Phraates is king of Parthia.
Vonones is the son of Phraates.
Vonones succeeds Phraates as king of Parthia.

"Phraates" refers to Phraates IV.

"Vonones" refers to Vonones I.

Tacitus, Annals 2.3:

Accordingly they summoned Artabanus, an Arsacid by blood, who had grown to manhood among the Dahae, and who, though routed in the first encounter, rallied his forces and possessed himself of the kingdom. The conquered Vonones found a refuge in Armenia, then a free country, and exposed to the power of Parthia and Rome, without being trusted by either, ...

Artabanus succeeds Vonones as king of Parthia.
Vonones seeks refuge in Armenia.

"Vonones" refers to Vonones I.

"Artabanus" refers to Artabanus II.

Some time earlier ...

..., without being trusted by either, in consequence of the crime of Antonius, who, under the guise of friendship, had inveigled Artavasdes, king of the Armenians, then loaded him with chains, and finally murdered him. His son, Artaxias, our bitter foe because of his father's memory, found defence for himself and his kingdom in the might of the Arsacids. When he was slain by the treachery of kinsmen, Caesar gave Tigranes to the Armenians, and he was put in possession of the kingdom under the escort of Tiberius Nero. But neither Tigranes nor his children reigned long, though, in foreign fashion, they were united in marriage and in royal power.

Artavasdes is king of Armenia.
Artaxias is the son of Artavasdes.
Artaxias succeeds Artavasdes as king of Armenia.
Tigranes succeeds Artaxias as king of Armenia.

"Artavasdes" refers to Artavasdes II; "Artaxias" refers to Artaxias II; "Tigranes" refers to Tigranes III.

Tacitus, Annals 2.4:

Next, at the bidding of Augustus, Artavasdes was set on the throne, nor was he deposed without disaster to ourselves. Caius Caesar was then appointed to restore order in Armenia. He put over the Armenians Ariobarzanes, a Mede by birth, whom they willingly accepted, because of his singularly handsome person and noble spirit. On the death of Ariobarzanes through a fatal accident, they would not endure his son. Having tried the government of a woman named Erato and having soon afterwards driven her from them, bewildered and disorganised, rather indeed without a ruler than enjoying freedom, they received for their king the fugitive Vonones.

Ariobarzanes becomes king of Armenia.
The son of Ariobarzanes becomes king of Armenia.
Erato becomes queen of Armenia.
Vonones becomes king of Armenia.

"Ariobarzanes" refers to Ariobarzanes II of Atropatene. "Vonones" refers to Vonones I.

Tacitus, Annals 2.42:

King Archelaus had been in possession of Cappadocia for fifty years, ...

Archelaus is king of Cappadocia.

During the same time, on the deaths of Antiochus and Philopator, kings respectively of the Commageni and Cilicians, these nations became excited, a majority desiring the Roman rule, some, that of their kings.

Antiochus is king of Commagene.
Philopator is king of Cilicia.

Tacitus, Annals 2.56:

It had at this time no king, Vonones having been expelled, but the nation's likings inclined towards Zeno, son of Polemon, king of Pontus, who from his earliest infancy had imitated Armenian manners and customs, loving the chase, the banquet, and all the popular pastimes of barbarians, and who had thus bound to himself chiefs and people alike. Germanicus accordingly, in the city of Artaxata, with the approval of the nobility, in the presence of a vast multitude, placed the royal diadem on his head. All paid him homage and saluted him as King Artaxias, which name they gave him from the city.

Vonones is no longer king of Armenia.
Polemon is king of Pontus.
Zeno is the son of Polemon.
Artaxias is king of Armenia.

"Vonones" refer to Vonones I. "Zeno" and "Artaxias" refer to Artaxias III; "Polemon" refers to Polemon I of Pontus.

Tacitus, Annals 2.79:

Meanwhile Domitius having landed at Laodicea, a city of Syria, as he was on his way to the winter-quarters of the sixth legion, which was, he believed, particularly open to revolutionary schemes, was anticipated by its commander Pacuvius.

Laodicea is a city in Syria.

Pacuvius is in commmand of the sixth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 4.1:

Of this the cause and origin was Aelius Sejanus, commander of the praetorian cohorts, of whose influence I have already spoken.

Aelius Sejanus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 4.73:

As soon as this was known to Lucius Apronius, pro-praetor of Lower Germany, he summoned from the Upper province the legionary veterans, as well as some picked auxiliary infantry and cavalry.

Lucius Apronius is in commmand of the lower army.

Apronius entrusted the rest of the auxiliaries to Cethegus Labeo, the commander of the fifth legion, ...

Cethegus Labeo is in commmand of the fifth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 6.15:

He next assigned some very vague reasons for his absence, then passed to more important matters, the ill-will against him originating in his state policy, and requested that Macro, who commanded the praetorians, with a few tribunes and centurions, might accompany him whenever he entered the Senate-house.

Macro is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 11.1:

Claudius made no further inquiry, but sent Crispinus, commander of the Praetorians, with troops in hot haste, as though to put down a revolt. Crispinus found him at Baiae, loaded him with chains, and hurried him to Rome.

Rufius Crispinus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 11.31:

First he questioned Turranius, superintendent of the corn market; next, Lusius Geta, who commanded the praetorians.

Caius Turranius is superintendent of the corn supplies.
Lusius Geta is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 12.40:

The emperor on hearing of the death of his representative appointed Aulus Didius in his place, that the province might not be left without a governor. Didius, though he quickly arrived, found matters far from prosperous, for the legion under the command of Manlius Valens had meanwhile been defeated, ...

Manlius Valens is in commmand of an unknown legion in Britain.

The legion under the command of Caesius Nasica fought with a similar result.

Caesius Nasica is in commmand of an unknown legion in Britain.

Tacitus, Annals 12.42:

till Agrippina did not yet dare to attempt her greatest scheme, unless Lusius Geta and Rufius Crispinus were removed from the command of the praetorian cohorts; for she thought that they cherished Messalina's memory and were devoted to her children.

Lusius Geta is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.
Rufius Crispinus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 12.44:

Vologeses was king of the Parthians; on the mother's side, he was the offspring of a Greek concubine, and he obtained the throne by the retirement of his brothers. Pharasmanes had been long in possession of Iberia, and his brother, Mithridates, ruled Armenia with our powerful support.

Vologeses is king of Parthia.
Pharasmanes is king of Iberia.
Mithridates is king of Armenia.
Mithridates is the brother of Pharasmanes.

"Vologeses" refers to Vologeses I. "Pharasmanes" refers to Pharasmanes I. "Mithridates" refers to Mithridates of Armenia.

There was a son of Pharasmanes named Rhadamistus, ...

Rhadamistus is the son of Pharasmanes.

Tacitus, Annals 12.48:

Quadratus, learning that Mithridates had been betrayed and that his kingdom was in the hands of his murderers, summoned a council, and, having informed them of what had occurred, consulted them whether he should take vengeance.

The death of Mithridates.
Rhadamistus is king of Armenia.

"Mithridates" refers to Mithridates of Armenia.

Tacitus, Annals 13.6:

With the close of the year came disquieting rumours that the Parthians had again broken their bounds and were ravaging Armenia, from which they had driven Rhadamistus, who, having often possessed himself of the kingdom and as often been thrust out of it, had now relinquished hostilities.

Parthian troops invade Armenia.
Rhadamistus is no longer king of Armenia.

Tacitus, Annals 13.7:

Lesser Armenia was intrusted to Aristobulus, Sophene to Sohaemus, each with the ensigns of royalty.

Aristobulus is king of Lesser Armenia.
Sohaemus is king of Sophene.

There rose up at this crisis a rival to Vologeses in his son Vardanes, and the Parthians quitted Armenia, apparently intending to defer hostilities.

Vardanes is the son of Vologeses.
Parthian troops withdraw from Armenia.

"Vardanes" refers to Vardanes II; "Vologeses" refers to Vologeses I.

Tacitus, Annals 13.8:

To their habitual flattery was added a real joy at his having appointed Domitius Corbulo to secure Armenia, thus opening, as it seemed, a field to merit. The armies of the East were so divided that half the auxiliaries and two legions were to remain in the province of Syria under its governor, Quadratus Ummidius; while Corbulo was to have an equal number of citizen and allied troops, together with the auxiliary infantry and cavalry which were in winter quarters in Cappadocia.

Domitius Corbulo is appointed to restore order in Armenia.
Quadratus Ummidius is governor of Syria.

Tacitus, Annals 13.15:

Pressed by Agrippina's menaces, having no charge against his brother and not daring openly to order his murder, he meditated a secret device and directed poison to be prepared through the agency of Julius Pollio, tribune of one of the praetorian cohorts, who had in his custody a woman under sentence for poisoning, Locusta by name, with a vast reputation for crime.

Julius Pollio is a tribune of a praetorian cohort.

Tacitus, Annals 13.28:

A contest arose between Vibullius, the praetor, and Antistius, a tribune of the people; ... It was further proposed by Lucius Piso, consul-elect, that tribunes were not to try any case in their own houses, ...

Vibullius is praetor.
Antistius is a tribune of the people.
Lucius Piso is consul-elect.

On this, Helvidius Priscus, a tribune of the people, followed up a personal quarrel he had with Obultronius Sabinus, one of the officials of the exchequer, ...

Helvidius Priscus is a tribune of the people.
Obultronius Sabinus is an official of the exchequer.

Tacitus, Annals 13.56:

Avitus, having written to Curtilius Mancia, commander of the Upper army, asking him to cross the Rhine and display his troops in the enemy's rear, himself led his legions into the territory of the Tencteri, and threatened them with extermination unless they dissociated themselves from the cause.

Curtilius Mancia is in commmand of the upper army.

Tacitus, Annals 14.32:

The victorious enemy met Petilius Cerialis, commander of the ninth legion, as he was coming to the rescue, routed his troops, and destroyed all his infantry.

Petilius Cerialis is in commmand of the ninth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 14.34:

Suetonius had the fourteenth legion with the veterans of the twentieth, and auxiliaries from the neighbourhood, to the number of about ten thousand armed men, when he prepared to break off delay and fight a battle.

Suetonius Paulinus is in commmand of the fourteenth legion and parts of the twentieth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 14.51:

For the emperor had appointed two men to the command of the praetorian cohorts, Faenius Rufus, for a vulgar popularity, which he owed to his administration of the corn-supplies without profit to himself; and Sofonius Tigellinus, whose inveterate shamelessness and infamy were an attraction to him. As might have been expected from their known characters, Tigellinus had the greater influence with the prince, and was the associate of his most secret profligacy, while Rufus enjoyed the favour of the people and of the soldiers, and this, he found, prejudiced him with Nero.

Faenius Rufus is a former superintendent of the corn supplies.
Faenius Rufus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.
Sofonius Tigellinus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 15.1:

Meanwhile, the Parthian king, Vologeses, when he heard of Corbulo's achievements and of a foreign prince, Tigranes, having been set over Armenia, ... Their anger was inflamed by Monobazus, who ruled the Adiabeni, ...

Vologeses is king of Parthia.
Tigranes is king of Armenia.
Monobazus is king of Adiabene.

Tacitus, Annals 15.2:

As for Media, Pacorus was already in possession of it.

Pacorus is king of Media.

Tacitus, Annals 15.3:

When Corbulo had heard all this from messengers he could trust, he sent two legions under Verulanus Severus and Vettius Bolanus to the support of Tigranes, ...

Verulanus Severus is in command of a legion.
Vettius Bolanus is in command of a legion.

Tacitus, Annals 15.6:

... and it was heard that Caesennius Paetus was on his way. And indeed he had now arrived, and the army was thus divided; the fourth and twelfth legions, with the fifth which had lately been raised in Moesia and the auxiliaries from Pontus, Galatia and Cappadocia, were under the command of Paetus, while the third, sixth, and tenth legions and the old soldiery of Syria remained with Corbulo.

Caesennius Paetus is in command of the fourth, twelfth and fifth legions in Syria.
Corbulo is in command of the third, sixth and tenth legions in Syria.

Tacitus, Annals 15.7:

Nor did Paetus decline the challenge, but with two legions, the 4th and 12th, the first of which was then commanded by Funisulanus Vettonianus and the second by Calavius Sabinus, entered Armenia, with unlucky omen.

Funisulanus Vettonianus is in command of the fourth legion.
Calavius Sabinus is in command of the twelfth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 15.28:

On the day appointed, Tiberius Alexander, a distinguished Roman knight, sent to assist in the campaign, and Vinianus Annius, Corbulo's son-in-law, who, though not yet of a senator's age, had the command of the fifth legion as "legatus," entered the camp of Tiridates, by way of compliment to him, and to reassure him against treachery by so valuable a pledge.

Vinianus Annius is in command of the fifth legion.

Tacitus, Annals 15.49:

That the leading spirits were Subrius Flavus, tribune of a praetorian cohort, and Sulpicius Asper, a centurion, was proved by the fearlessness of their death.

Subrius Flavus is tribune of a praetorian cohort.
Sulpicius Asper is a centurion.

Tacitus, Annals 15.50:

Besides Subrius and Sulpicius, whom I have already mentioned, they invited the aid of military strength, of Gavius Silvanus and Statius Proximus, tribunes of praetorian cohorts, and of two centurions, Maximus Scaurus and Venetus Paulus.

Gavius Silvanus is tribune of a praetorian cohort.
Statius Proximus is tribune of a praetorian cohort.
Maximus Scaurus is a centurion.
Venetus Paulus is a centurion.

Tacitus, Annals 15.72:

Then, as if he was going to describe successes in war, he summoned the Senate, and awarded triumphal honours to Petronius Turpilianus, an ex-consul, to Cocceius Nerva, praetor-elect, and to Tigellinus, commander of the praetorians.

Sofonius Tigellinus is in commmand of the Praetorian Guard.

Tacitus, Annals 15.74:

I find in the registers of the Senate that Cerialis Anicius, consul-elect, proposed a motion that a temple should as soon as possible be built at the public expense to the Divine Nero.

Cerialis Anicius is consul-elect.